# Vyas **Ramasubramani**

🛘 (+1) 408-421-2162 | 💌 vyas.ramasubramani@gmail.com | 🏕 vyasr.com | 🖸 vyasr | 🕏 Vyas | 🛅 vyas-ramasubramani | 📂 Vyas

# Summary.

I am a PhD candidate at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. I use molecular simulations and machine learning methods to study the self-assembly of proteins and nanoparticles into complex structures. I both lead and contribute to a number of open-source Python and C/C++ projects in my research area, including freud, HOOMD-blue, and signac, and have contributed to other tools in the SciPy stack. I have experience optimizing code in various languages and on both CPU and GPU architectures, and I have made use of tools like CuPy, cuDF, and numba to do so in Python. I also have worked in containerized environments for HPC resources and continuous integration, and I help maintain containers for ongoing research use.

# **Education**

Ph.D. IN CHEMICAL ENGINEERING AND SCIENTIFIC COMPUTING - UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN

M.S. IN CHEMICAL ENGINEERING - UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN

B.S.E. IN CHEMICAL ENGINEERING - PRINCETON UNIVERSITY

2009 - 2013

Minors: Quantitative and Computational Biology, Applications of Computing

# **Work and Research Experience**

#### RESEARCH ASSISTANT - UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN - GLOTZER GROUP

Oct 2015 - Present

- · Developed a new simulation technique for the molecular dynamics of anisotropic particles and optimized it for modern GPUs.
- Employed a novel coarse-graining approach to explain the assembly of supercharged protein oligomers.
- Built machine learning models to identify key drivers of protein crystallization.
- Developed and implemented models of implicit solvation including parallelization via MPI and OpenMP.

#### SENIOR FINANCIAL ANALYST - D.C. ENERGY LLC

Sep 2013 - Jul 2015

- Increased trade profitability by combining powerflow analysis and various financial metrics to enhance automated trade optimization.
- Modernized the company's data infrastructure by improving web scraping frameworks, database design, and analytical algorithms.
- Built web tools using R, PHP, JavaScript, and MySQL to aid technical and fundamental market analysis.

#### THESIS RESEARCHER - PRINCETON UNIVERSITY - PRUD'HOMME LAB

Sep 2012 - Jun 2013

- Characterized phase separation in specific polymer blends to ameliorate effects of depletion flocculation.
- Developed nanoparticles and gel microparticles for incorporation into a targeted drug delivery system for lung cancer.

### Skills

**Languages** EXPERT: Python, C++ ADVANCED: C, R, MySQL, MATLAB INTERMEDIATE: Java, Cuda, PHP, JavaScript **Tools & Frameworks** Python packages: scikit-learn, TensorFlow, Keras, pandas, NumPy, numba Parallelism: MPI, OpenMP, TBB

# **Selected Projects**

#### LEAD DEVELOPER - SIGNAC FRAMEWORK (GITHUB.COM/GLOTZERLAB/SIGNAC)

- · Co-led development of a NumFOCUS-affiliated project for data and workflow management in Python.
- · Enabled flexible, easy-to-use storage mechanism for research data in computational science and machine learning.
- Drove development of a new, compact API for workflow definition.

#### LEAD DEVELOPER - FREUD (GITHUB.COM/GLOTZERLAB/FREUD)

- Co-led development of a C++ tool with Cython-generated Python bindings for fast, TBB-multithreaded analysis of molecular simulations.
- · Spearheaded the creation of a standardized API achieving a high degree of flexibility and consistency.
- Standardized memory handling to simplify the user interface and minimize data copying.
- Achieved 3-15x performance improvements across the package as part of the 2.0 release.

## CORE DEVELOPER - HOOMD-BLUE (GITHUB.COM/GLOTZERLAB/HOOMD-BLUE)

- Made various contributions to a general purpose, high-performance particle simulation toolkit for GPU-accelerated molecular dynamics and Monte Carlo simulations that is currently one of NVIDIA's official HPC benchmarks.
- Enabled bidirectional MPI communication to enable multi-body force fields in MPI simulations.
- Implemented the Gilbert-Johnson-Keerthi algorithm on CPUs and GPUs as part of an anisotropic pair potential.

# **Honors & Awards**

Jul 2019 Beyster Computational Innovation Fellow, University of Michigan

Apr 2019 2nd Place, MICDE Symposium Poster Competition

Sep 2018 Fellow, Michigan Institute for Computational Discovery & Engineering